<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unprofitable servants talent put into the bank, in sure hope of acceptance by a merciful Lord; or, The mean mans gift towards the helping forward of the Lords great work. With an information and message from the Lord, to all sorts of people concerned herein; written in plain simplicity.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10222</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80924968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U92B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185872</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80924968</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80924968</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192133</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10222)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192133)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2900:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unprofitable servants talent put into the bank, in sure hope of acceptance by a merciful Lord; or, The mean mans gift towards the helping forward of the Lords great work. With an information and message from the Lord, to all sorts of people concerned herein; written in plain simplicity.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with slight loss of text; p. 11-14 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clergy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious leaders --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192133:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The unprofitable Servants Talent put into the Bank, in ſure hope of acceptance by a merciful Lord; Or, the mean mans Gift towards the helping forward of the Lords Great Work. With An Information and Meſſage from the Lord, to all ſorts of People concerned herein; written in plain ſimplicity.</head>
            <p>TRuly beloved friends, if you will with an impartial eye ſeriouſly mind theſe following diſcoveries made and confirmed by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from the Lord, you ſhall find ſomewhat diſcovered of the right deſcent and aſcent of the true Goſpel-Miniſtry, and of their Parſonages, Pattents and Inductions, as they are ordained and ſent forth by the Lord and own'd of him; and alſo ſomewhat of ſuch as are ſent by and from men that run before they are ſent of the chief Governour and Head of his Church, (Chriſt Jeſus) of whom he declares that ſuch are Theeves, &amp; Robbers, and come forth for that end; and truly as far as I am able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover my heart herein, I have no other end, nor reſpect of perſons in me in writing of this by the Lords teaching of me, then had either <hi>Elijah;</hi> or <hi>Iſaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, Paul,</hi> or any other that declared againſt thoſe falſe Teachers in their times that the Lord diſowned; or for any further end then
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192133:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>what the Lord appears in to be with or againſt them: And if you judge me in what I have ſaid from the Lord herein, I can well bear it, and rejoyce that in this one addition to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſenſible complaints gone forth againſt falſhood and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in thoſe that call themſelves Miniſters of Chriſt: That what I have written I was taught it immediately of and by the Lord, and not by or from men; I beſeech you weigh it, for it will be found true, that much lies in hazard in that very thing, though little regarded by the moſt; its no leſs then Land liberties, State ſouls of men, yea all we are, &amp; do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect or enjoy, and then certainly its time to look about us, or elſe it never will be: But it may be you will ſay, this is but ſome giddy conceit of a buſie head: but before you paſs your cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thereon, do like <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> conſider and conſult, whether the Lord or man moſt clearly appears in it. Firſt, Obſerve well what the Lord hath done for us and to us here in theſe Nations. Whether it be not as much or more then he did too and for thoſe that he hath ſeverely judged for unfruitful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or unprofitable Servants, and know that the Lord is the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever, and will certainly judge us as ſeverely if we repent not ſpeedily, becauſe he is God and changeth not, but in hope of mercy will be pray that thus adviſeth you from the Lord, and wait for the viſion until the appointed time, having his eyes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what opened by the Lord, but was born blind, and ſo lived more then fifty years; and there was never any heard of that ever could or did do ſuch a cure, but onely the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is the ſame from and to eternity; therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware how you ſlight his workings in or upon any of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Sons of men, for then they will witneſs againſt you, and ſay, its a marvellous thing that you diſcern not whence this work is; but conſider it well that few of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers or people did then believe: neither is it diſcernable that many yet do. But my hopes are great of ſome of ours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that many of them have not onely ſaid, but have yielded up to dye for the liberty of the pure Goſpel, though fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſcured to them by deceivers: And upon theſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more good grounds, will I ſtill hope, wait, and pray for the incoming of the Goſpel Glory into theſe deſpiſed Nations,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192133:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>though fearfully blind and inſenſible of it, and ſo ſecure in the middle of danger, and willing to remain as they are; as the many addreſſes printed witneſs ſadly; but conſider I pray, that the Lord comes as the Lightning, ſuddenly, terribly, and openly in Glorious brightneſs, and as a Thief in the night; therefore its declared to be the beſt wiſdome for every one to be watching in that place his Lord hath ſet him in, leſt he come ſuddenly and find them out of order, and give them that ſad portion threatned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. and further know, that the Lord is not ſlack as ſome think, and ſay too; neither ſhall one tittle of his word fail to be fully accompliſhed in its own due time. I beſeech you conſider that are in high places, that if the miniſtry be not right that you ſet up the guilt will be a very ſad one to you; for it is the price of ſouls, that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the ſight of the Lord, and to be guilty of the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one, will prove to be of more loſs to them then the loſs of their lives, honours, and what elſe you are, or do enjoy; and do not think I am too bold with you; for its in true love to and pity of your ſouls, and in due reſpect to your perſons and office; ſome amongſt you that know me, will engage for me in that, if I need, I dare ſay it.</p>
            <p>Beloved friends, becauſe the difference is high amongſt us about the Goſpel Miniſtry, whether it be to be found in or amongſt the Pariſh Prieſts or Parſons, or in and amongſt the truly godly, that are called of God, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was. Of the firſt ſort few ſuch appear plainly I fear, and alſo becauſe my ſelf, and many more of which ſome are truly godly, I doubt not have found by many fad experiences, the uneffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualneſs of the publique parties Miniſtry, eſpecialy of late times, and having obtained mercy of the Lord, I declare my judgment therein, who if I were known unto the world, my labour I fear ſhould be ſlighted, the rather becauſe of my meanneſs; and I know and believe that I write theſe things by the teaching of the Lord Spirit; and if you will ſearch the Scriptures with me,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.3.12.</note> we ſhall ſurely find whether the preaching of the Goſpel be from Heaven or of men; for it te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies clearly thereof; but I fear that the moſt will belie the truth, although it be clearly manifeſted in and through the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192133:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Scriptures,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.9.14.</note> that its of and from God and Chriſt alone, although men are made inſtuments and tongues a help; yet prophecy which is of the immediate teaching of God, exceeds all for the edifying of the Church, which is the declaring of the mind of God,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.10, 11.</note> by that man alone that is taught of God; but Tongues are for a ſign, and a ſad one too; therefore truſt not too much in them. Conſider then, Is it not very neceſſary that diligent ſearch ſhould be made herein; that ſo the ſpirits of ſuch as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to preach, may be fully diſcerned whether they be of Chriſt or not?
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.2.</note> For many deceivers are foretold to come forth in after times, and ſhall deceive many; let us therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of them, and take good heed that we be not deceived by them now, though they cry errors in others; for it is the Thiefs policy to cry <hi>Keep Thief,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> 13.21.23. <hi>Jude</hi> 4.16. <hi>Prov</hi> 14.15.</note> when he is in danger to be diſcovered, and the Whores practiſe to cry <hi>Whore</hi> firſt; for if it be poſſible they will deceive the very Elect; thoſe will not indure to be proved by the pure light of God that ſhines in any man becauſe they being blinded by ſin and ſelfe wiſedom cannot abide nor diſcern it; the only way to me diſcovered is to try them by the Scriptures, becauſe the moſt of them make that their defence; and thereby will plainly appear who they are that are ſent of God, called and choſen, and who they are that run before they are ſent,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9.12.</note> and by their fruits let both ſorts of them be known and owned; for then is nothing hid, ſo that it cannot be made manifeſt; but in the trying of them beware of the Leaven or Doctrine of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes, which is hypocriſie, which conſiſteth wholly in form and outward waſhings,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.9.</note> and workes of that nature; for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Leaven leaveneth the whole lump; and when they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, let what is clear of them, be declared upon the houſe tops, that they being known may be avoided, that ſo they may no longer deceive and deſtroy poor ignorant ſouls by their deluſions,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.1.4.15.17.</note> nor Satan have ſuch a party undiſcovered, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do miſchief by ſtill.</p>
            <p>The firſt order of Prieſts or Preachers that we read of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Scriptures, was <hi>Noah</hi> and his Progenitors and Succeſſors and was not he and they immediately called of God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be Preachers of righteouſneſs, and he was a juſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192133:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>man that walked with God, and perfect in a Corrupt Age or Generation, and righteous before God in his Generation, and a pure worſhipper of God, and he was bleſſed of God, and was ſeparated from the World and their wayes, and was no doubt their ſcorn, yet ſtedfaſt with the Lord, and owned of God; but of what Univerſity, or School was he of, or where lay his Parſonage, Pariſh or Penſion, tell me if you can? or where had he his induction or Ordination, or by whom had he it, if not from the Lord alone; then ſurely he can ſtill do it if need be, and there is no doubt of it,
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.6.</note> but few ſuch we ſee or here of now.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Prieſt we read of in the Scriptures, was <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeek,</hi> of whom much is to be ſpoken if we were not dull of hearing: This man was immediately ſent of God, and call'd the Prieſt of the moſt high God, and the true type of the pure ſeed and Son of God, Chriſt Jeſus, and ſuch are all true Goſpel-Miniſters, for they have learned of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Ezechi. 44.25.20.</note> Oh my dear friends conſider, are our publick Preachers true <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedicks;</hi> or do they appear to be call'd and ſent of God immediately as he was, for he was without Father or Mother, that were of the pure ſeed to train or breed him up to that office by their inſtruction,
<note place="margin">Gen. 10.19.12.</note> or to ſet them to Schools of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learning? or be our publique Miniſters true living types, and not lying dead members of Chriſt? are they Prieſts of righteouſneſs and Peace? ſuch are or ought to be all Chriſts Miniſters wholly harmleſs, ſeparate from ſinners. <hi>Melchiz.</hi> met <hi>Abraham</hi> and bleſſed him for reſcuing the pure Seed,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 7.8.</note> and the righteous ſoul that was vex'd at their uncleanneſs, own ſuch for the Prieſts of God, and I will vote with you; but are our Pariſh Preachers ſuch that are approv'd of, and ſent by men chiefly from Schools of humane learning, if not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, what pure work of ſpiritual light &amp; life moves friends and them thereunto, that appears to the view of any Godly but chiefly preferments in the world, do they witneſs that they are ſent of God to ſet up Chriſts Kingdom as fellow-helpers, or by bleſſing ſuch as are made Inſtruments of God to reſcue the pure ſeed of God out of the power of cruel ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? I fear not many of them, but rather curſe them, except
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192133:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>their own outward advantages appear in chiefly, witneſs love and his confederacy, and Dr. <hi>Hewet,</hi> and many more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in thoſe times, that were eaſily diſcerned: Are they ſuch:
<note place="margin">Sam. 2.12.17.</note> are they ſuch as <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed gives Tythes to, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſacrificing: or do they not rather take them by force, like the ſervants of wicked <hi>Hophney</hi> and <hi>Phineas,</hi> of the pure ſeed for carnal ends. Is not Tythes and Gleabes, and ſuch like that draws them to places? and not conſcience for to bleſs the faithful Children of <hi>Abraham?</hi> I fear it is, for very few ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be bleſſed by them, in their Pariſhes and their riding and running to and fro to beg and get Letters, and hands to mediate for them, and to ſubſcribe their lying Certificates, and that of the very prophane and ignorant people, to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie them to be Orthodox, that underſtand not what it is, nor oft-times never heard them; did <hi>Melchiz.</hi> thus, and yet they cry up him for a Preſident for them, to make out their Title to their Tythes by. O wretched men! that dare thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude into the pure Prieſtly office for ſelf ends, and by corrupt wayes and meanings, which is an holy calling all that feare God,
<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.3, 7, 8.9.</note> diſown ſuch, and ſo will I, for God diſowns and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours them both, and then woe be to them that ſet and keep them up, if they repent not ſpeedily, let ſuch know they are but men that reſiſt the Lord thereby, and be they never ſo Great, he will judge.</p>
            <p>This third order of Prieſts recorded in Scriptures, is the Tribe of <hi>Levy,</hi> which includes both the offices of Prieſts and Levites, in it are our Preachers and Parſonage-mongers like the Tribe of <hi>Levy,</hi> as they uſe to call themſelves? I am ſure the Tribe of <hi>Levy</hi> was not trained upon the two well Heads, or Nurſeries of learning, as the Engliſh Prieſts uſe to call them in their Pulpit-prayers, I wiſh they be not Nurſeries of luſt,
<note place="margin">Exod. 1.3.14. Exod. 4.10.</note> where many of our Prieſts are bred: but the Brick kilnes were <hi>Levies</hi> breeding places, and in Egypt's bondage; neither were they ſent into their office by men firſt, but they came in at the Lords call to deliver Iſrael from their bondage; and afterwards when Iſrael had fallen fouly, then they took the, Lords part freely at the firſt call againſt the Claf-worſhippers <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.26, 29. and the Lord own'd them for it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192133:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>them for an offering to himſelf, to ſerve about the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, and ſerved them to bleſs in his name,
<note place="margin">Numb. 3.45.</note> and the Lord was their portion and inheritance, and he was their Teacher, and he ſaid that they muſt be really pure as they were tipifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they denyed their neareſt relations for the Lord, and their Parſonages were larger or leſſer, as they turn'd few or many to righteouſneſs; and if any of them polluted any of the holy things or themſelves, they were to be cut off, and they were to be out of the worlds ways and orders, and they muſt be men grown, and not boys, nor old decay'd ones that might ſerve either in the Prieſts office, or about the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle; neither were any of them approved of that, oppoſed the power and purity of Godlineſs in any, and they were to marry purely, and to have pure families, and their greateſt care and endeavour was to honour Gods great name both in life, Doctrine, ſuch and much more were the true Levitical Prieſthood, and ſuch I own, and ſo I deſire you ſhould, and then you will be truly honourable, and much honoured by God and all good men. But good friends conſider with me, are our pariſh Prieſthood ſuch, or ſo call'd, or come in as theſe, I cannot diſcern it to be ſo; Do they come in as gods to execute judgement on the wicked corrupters of Religion; Nay do they not uphold ſtill much ſuperſtition both in places and forms; are not the moſt of them call'd in by men like themſelves and are not the chief ends that they purſue that are diſcernable, Parſonages, Tythes, Lordſhips, over mens Conſciences, and ſatisfaction to their fleſhly luſts do they rebuke plainly all offences againſt all God or man in Patrons, friends, and all others, or own all truths as they are revealed: Nay verily they oppoſe many plain truths, and flatter the moſt of People, and tell them its lawful when its poyſonous and diſtructive to young and old, as vain ſports for recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, exceſſive feaſting, and vain toyiſh coſtly Houſes, habits, and adornings, and ſuch like; and do they not call many a pure truth an error, becauſe their dark minds nor old Authors diſcern'd nor diſcover them not; Oh how few of them take the Lords part againſt wicked ones and wickedneſs, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially againſt that of the Calfs that it remains here, may rather
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192133:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>like blinde <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they aſcribe deliverance to it, becauſe it was their old Religion. Do they bleſſe the people in the Lords name? It little appears by their ſucceſſes; for very few appear to be bleſſed in moſt of their Pariſhes, as they call them, but remain a poor blinde, dead-hearted people to pure godlineſſe, to the great grief of many: Or do they, or dare they make the Lord their portion? not one of a hundred of them, I fear; but rather Parſonages, Penſions, Augmentations, &amp; the like; &amp; if theſe reach not to make them as large as they deſire, then they ſeek for an additional help, by an Hoſpital, or a Lecture, or ſome ignorant great one to be a Chaplain too or by a School, or Phiſick, or ſome ſuch way, too many of them; or elſe they wait for a call to a greater (but never to a leſſer) profit. Oh Prieſts, bluſh for ſhame! Did ever any of the Lords Prieſts thus? and do not moſt of you ſeek proud wives inſtead of pure ones, to ſerve your luſts, rather then to grace your Office; and do not moſt of you breed vain Children inſtead of godly ones? Levitical Prieſts were taught of God, but ours at Univerſities, or by Authors that lived in dark days: If the Levitical Prieſts polluted the Holy things, or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they were to be cut off; but the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> hold all by life, though many of them, fearfully polluted by covetous, earthly, proud, vain, ignorant, malicious ſpirits, &amp;c. until of late, and yet few found inſufficient by their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brethren, that are appointed to try them, if ordained in and by their Antichriſtian Order: It is ſad to behold, that by thoſe authorized, they, their wives and children, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered before the ſouls of men and women; let the knowledge of this, turn your mirth into mourning that are Rulers: Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, the Levitical Prieſts were to be ſeparated from the worlds ways and orders, but none deeper in them then Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Prieſts; the Levitical Prieſts were neither to begin young nor to continue old, but <hi>Englands</hi> Prieſts begin boys, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main until impotency; <hi>Levy</hi> forſook the neereſt relations, and the higheſt outward advantages for God and his cauſe, but Engliſh Prieſts forſake God, and Chriſt, and his Government for the world; <hi>Levy</hi> in the Prieſthood ſought to exalt the great and glorious name of God above all things, but the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192133:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> diſhonour it fearfully, eſpecially the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Juſtice, and Mercy of God, both in Doctrine and Practice; but ſuch as they are, lived in thoſe times, and the Lord ſent his faithful true Prophets and Servants to declare againſt them; and ſo he doth now, but they then ſlighted them, until judgement came upon the whole Nation, and its much to be feared that it will be ſo now with us; for we ſmart already, and more is likely to follow, except ſpeedy repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſtop it, for our mock-faſts neither have, nor will do it any longer: O learn wiſdom whilſt it is to day, both Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, Prieſts, and People, before the Decree come forth, and there be no remedy: And think it not a vain thing, that ſo many cry againſt the Prieſts now, and that godly ones too (or elſe, I fear, few godly will be found in <hi>England</hi>) is it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Lord? nay, judge all you people, hath not the Lord himſelf caſt dung in their faces, and curſed their bleſſings? Do they turn many, nay, ſcarce any to righteouſneſs? Are not the moſt of their beſt Auditors meer ignorant formaliſts? And are not they weary of Gods ſervice, and preach by a glaſs, and look oft at it, leſt it out laſt their notes; yet cry, they would not be tedious, to keep their credit, and pleaſe poor ignorant carnal people: Had not the Lord by the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery taken away ſome of our fooleries, we ſhould ſtill have been as we were before, or worſe, if Prieſts might have had their wills; but own ſuch for the Lords Miniſters who will, I dare not, until I ſee them better, for I am ſure they are not right according to Scripture, nor like the preſidents there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded; and therefore I diſown them, and ſo ought you that I write to, or elſe wo be to you. But it may be, that many of them in the publike Miniſtrey will be ſo fool hardy as to ſay (excepting their plea for Tythes thereby) That they are called into that Office, under a higher Diſpenſation of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Order then the Levitical Prieſthood was, and that they are Miniſters of a better Covenant, that is given upon better promiſes: But if ye ſay ſo, then ſay I, look to what is ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57 16, 17 18. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30.</note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1. and then wo be to you if you preach not the pure Goſpel purely, without mixtures, either of addition or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution. And if you plead thus, then tell us from whom you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:192133:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſucced, whether from <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> or Chriſt, or his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Diſciples, or of and from the Evangeilſt Teachers and Paſtors of the primitive Ordination, tell us, that we may prove you by them there; will you put your ſelves upon the tryal there, if you do, you will be found too ſhort yet of the pattern a great deal; for its more pure then you can with thoſe Eyes that yet you ſee by, diſcover or declare to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Conſider friends, whether the Baptiſm and Preaching of <hi>John</hi> were from heaven or of men: He was the firſt New Teſtament Goſpel Preacher, and ſanctified from the womb, and not in a School or Parſonage; but few of you Miniſters appear to be ſo, after many years ſtanding in your Office; and he came neither eating nor drinking, daintily, nor in coſtly Apparel, but moſt of you, if you can get them any way, come in all theſe to the height of them; and I fear, affect them more then the Goſpel, <hi>John</hi> came preaching and baptizing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to repentance; but few of you declare what it is; and I am ſure thoſe I ſee, act not aright in their places, and many preach contrary, and cannot declare whether faith or repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is firſt to be acted by their Converts: And <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>That the Kingdom of God was at hand;</hi> but you ſay, It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready come, and yet you cannot declare it, at leaſt, you do not, and when it will come, you know not, if that be not it that you preach to poor blinde people, which is nothing like it, and yet you would have them reſt in it, where no true reſt is to be found; for nothing its elſe that you declare to them but to hear you, and to perform ſome ſuch fervices as you can teach them, all which are meer formalities; and Chriſt ſaid of <hi>John,</hi> That he was a burning and ſhining light; and which of you are ſo, or declare what it is to be ſuch a one; and <hi>John</hi> did not take his firſt viſions of Chriſt to be the full manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him to reſt in, but inquired further of him as one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied therewith of his fulneſs; but moſt of you ſtay in the beginning of light, and labour not to get towards per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection but rather decline for ought that can be diſcerned; and ſo ſhut up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt your ſelves and others: And <hi>John</hi> was a plain and full rebuker of ſin in all <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                  <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:192133:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of, or by ſuch onely as are enlightned, called, renewed, and taught of the Lord alone, far above all mens teachings, and ſuch onely are Chriſts true Miniſters, and to be owned. And now, O ye Prieſts, I call ye to ſpeak once more in your own defence (but either ſpeak right words, or elſe be ſilent, for diſcerning ſpirits are come forth) and ſhew if you can, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> or any of the whole Prieſthoods order forenamed, were called in by men, or had either Pariſh, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, or any ſuch limitted order or place as yours, or that their tythes and wages were as yours are; but contrary, for they were free offerings, as the yearly feaſts were, and in them the fatherleſſe, the ſtranger, the widow, and the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite did eat and rejoyce together before the Lord: There was neither tythe Calf nor Gooſe brought to the Parſonage nor Vicarage houſes, neither had the miſtreſſe nor her maids authority to gather tythe eggs or apples of the poor and needy. That that was tythed in Iſrael was brought in freely to worſhip the Lord with and by it. But ye, O Prieſts, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the poor, the widdow and others by yours, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God thereby. Are you or any other able to make it appear that thoſe are right Laws, Statutes, Judgements and Ordinances, that yours are eſtabliſhed and required by, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the right Government of a Chriſtian Nation that are taught of the Lord? I know the contrary. O blinde leaders of the blinde! will you both fall into the ditch? ſtop ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, left you periſh, and get better Guides; for light is broken forth, ſhut not your eyes againſt it, but behold it, and walk in it whilſt it appears, leſt darkneſſe come ſpeedily, and then you may ſo ſtumble and fall, that you can never riſe again. O conſider this, you that have long forgotten the Lord, <hi>leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you,</hi> becauſe of the ſlighting of his calls when he would have healed you: But I tell you plainly, that Goſpel Miniſters ſhould firſt be Elders in the faith, before they enter into that high Office, and not Novices in the ſalvation of God, ſhould thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into it; for none can diſcern it, but by the Holy Ghoſt given into them; neither can any miniſter that to others, which they have not received, for the carnal minde is in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192133:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>againſt the ſpiritual gifts of God and Chriſt; neither can they know them, nor preach them really to others, and if they be not firſt reconciled in themſelves, how can they ſhow the reconciliation of the ſoul into Chriſts pure nature unto others, to lead them up unto it, or the knowledge of it, that they may labour to grow forward to be wrought into it fully, that ſo they may become holy, as the Lord is holy, and to be meek and lowly, as Chriſt is, that ſo they may finde reſt to their ſouls: and for the gaining this, they muſt firſt be humble in the ſenſe of their own blindeneſſe, and then the promiſe is from the Lord that he will teach them, and give them grace and glory, and ſuch own for right Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and none elſe; for this is the Lords way of exalting men into Goſpel gifts of grace. Are ours ſuch in publique places, I fear few of them. Aſk them further, Have ye a true call from the Lord to that Office? and they will ſay, Yea: But if you will conſider them by what is before writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, it will appear contrary, as alſo by the teſtimony of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Scriptures; and therefore let them know this for themſelves, that the Councel of the Lord ſhall ſtand, and although Circumciſion be commanded by the Lord, yet when that that is figured by it is come, it muſt ceaſe, without a written command, and then they that are circumciſed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, can have no profit by Chriſt: Take heed what you do, the Lord is not mocked, what ye ſow, that ye muſt reap, friends: I bear record to you, that you have a little zeal, and a little ſtrength, but its ready to dye, and it is not according to right knowledge, elſe you never would hold up, depend upon, nor own ſuch for right Goſpel ways as you do. Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord give you underſtanding: For if you perſiſt thus, the Lord will ſuddenly deſtroy you, as he did your Predeceſſors; for certainly he is come forth to judge the World in righteouſneſs, and a ſhort worke will he make upon the earth; for by his own arm will he bring in ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; for ſurely our hopes by men of might is low, whilſt we hear of and behold ſuch a wicked crue of Lawyers in our Parliament, who will neither enter into Chriſt's Kingdome, nor ſuffer others to go in that would; but as this ſtartled
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:192133:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Scribes and Phariſees, ſo it will them;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>and</hi> 11.45. <hi>to</hi> 54, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</note> but the Lord will deſtroy them all if they repent not ſpeedily, though ſome of their own Tribe ſay, they are the moſt rational men in the Parliament, and that they do very good ſervice there, yet it's much doubted of; for not one of a hundred of them appears to ſeek ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, that they might come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſalvation, and then what good can be expected by them? beware now that diſcontent ariſe not againſt my plain and high words to you; for they are trutly in care of and love to your poor ſouls, that are in danger to periſh moſt of them, although Chriſt bought them, for none can ſee his Kingdom that is not new born, and how few know what that is? as appears ſadly, though maſters in <hi>England,</hi> yea Fathers and Teachers alſo; therefore woe to them that are taught and ruled by ſuch. Hath the Lord wrought ſo great delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances for us, as no other Nation we hear of hath received or had the like? and do we thus require the Lord? Oh fooliſh and and unwiſe people, that forget or neglect ſo great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, be ſure the Lord will mind us of them more ſharply the next time he viſits us, who inſtead of feeding his Lambs, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to Lord it over his heritage by heavy oppreſſions, that are laid upon them both in and out of Priſons, and in our profeſſion are become meer Formaliſts again, and have turn'd both preaching and profeſſion into meer pratings moſt of them, yea into railings, both in Writings and Pulpits; and you cauſed to be impriſoned many an innocent, hungry and thirſty ſoul, that was ſeeking after the Lord Jeſus Chriſt and his fulneſs. How think you, Oh Prieſts and Rulers, that you can eſcape the greateſt damnation, that thus deal ſtill with poor ſouls, that have been long deluded by you, that have cried ſo here, and there, and yet never did nor could manifeſt Chriſt to them, nor yet like <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> would you ſay, That is not he.</p>
            <p>Oh Souldiers at laſt, (before it be too late) call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance what you ſaw and ingaged for and againſt at the firſt, under Noble <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and his Officers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> and go up to <hi>Bethel</hi> and pay your vowes to the Lord for he delights not in ſuch fools that vow and perform not; remember where and how oft he hath appeared to and for you, and own the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:192133:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lord in all your Victories, by following him fully, and then you are ſure to go into the promiſed Land, when others will be ſhut out, and your enemies muſt ſtill fly before you, and you ſhall ſtill be a terrour to them, and in ſo doing the Lord will bleſs you with the reſt of his faithful ones; and you ſhall certainly rejoyce together; but if you loſe your firſt loves, and grow lukewarm in and unto his cauſe, except you ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent and do your firſt work, you muſt and will loſe your Glory, and be ſpu'd out and fall ſhort of the Glory of his Saints, and what is your gain then and reward for all your adventures, take heed therefore that you neglect not the Lords calls that are ſent to you, and ſay not that the time is not yet, leaſt he judge you for it, beware you reſt not in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace, glory and victories, but like the two Tribes and a halfe, go on before your Brethren, until all theirs and your Enemies are ſubdued, and then you ſhall certainly return to your poſſeſſions in Peace and Comfort; but if you ſlight the Lords Calls, and ſay they are but deceipts and deluſions, my ſoul ſhall weep in ſecret for you before the Lord, that he may rouſe you up ſome other way, that you may not loſe your reward, for many of you are Worthyes, and ſome that are caſt off alſo. I wiſh they may be all owned that are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right hearted, and that all needleſs jealouſies may ceaſe, and that vengeance may be left to the Lord, and revenges ceaſe amongſt you, and that you would do no violence to any, and be content each one with his own right wages, for certainly the Lord will render to every one according to his works (without reſpect of perſons) as they are continued in unto the end; be wiſe therefore O ye Rulers, Commanders. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and Judges of theſe Nations of the Earth, and ſerve the Lord with fear, faithfulneſs, and trembling, and kiſs the Son (that now gloriouſly appears) leaſt ye periſh from the way; and if my poor counſel may be found uſeful in any thing, I ſhall greatly rejoyce in the Lord for it, that certainly ſet me a work, and carried me through it in the midſt of many op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, high fears, and many objections, for none of it is mine that hath any wiſdome appearing in it, but its wholly of the Lord; but if I may prevail no further, grant theſe few
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:192133:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>things at my requeſt; I entreat you firſt, that as there hath been given forth ſtrict Commands with penalties, for the Prieſts peaceable preaching, and paſſing to and from their meeting places; ſo would alſo command, that when they have preached at any time, that then they may be required to clear to ſuch as doubt of their doctrine, thoſe things that by tender Conſciences are then ſcrupled and peaceably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them, and certainly thereby truth and deceit will be both made manifeſt moſt eaſily and ſpeedily, and poor igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people eaſily informed in the truth,; and alſo that the Prieſts and their Diſciples may have the like freedom given them. Secondly, that you would take a more ſtrict and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect care and courſe to prove ſuch by as are to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into that high office, then yet hath been taken by our former Governours for that end, that onely ſuch perſons as do clearly appear to be taught of God themſelves, may prove them and thoſe alſo that are already admitted into that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and to put by all ſuch (without partiality as are found) by them unfit and unworthy of that place that ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns every one in an high degree. Thirdly, that you would take care that all ſuch as are found meet to preach the pure Goſpel, and would do it freely, may have liberty and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection by you, and then no doubt you will preſently have many empty Parſonages to help to maintain publique char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for the eaſe of poor ſubjects, and ſatisfying publick debts that are the Nations ſhame, and ſin both. Fourthly, That you would take a courſe (which eaſily may be done, and for great advantages every way) to take off the paying Tythes in kind, and cauſe them all to be put upon moderate Rents to each particular perſon from whom they are due; which thing may be eaſily done, and it will be found to be of great good uſe, both for the ſouls and eſtates of all people that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned therein. Fifthly. That you take order, to have utterly thrown down that moſt wicked oppreſſing Law that remains in this Nation, and that courſe may be taken, that wrongs may be rectified in a Chriſtian-like way and manner Sixthly, That that ſhameful and ſhameleſs ſort of people, that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as Rogues up and down the Nation, to our great ſin and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:192133:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhame, may be ſuppreſſed. Laſtly, That you would take care that our Elections of Councils, may be made by ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as are found moſt fit and able to Counſel, &amp; to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled in the fear of God; for our confuſed Elections have been and will be improfitable and uſeleſs; more very needful work there is to be done, that I would willingly inform you of, but I ſhall rejoyce to ſee theſe forenamed well ordered; for that will give good hopes of the future; but if you prove no better then moſt of our former Rulers, I will give over looking for help by men, and pray and wait for helpe and deliverance from the Lord ſome other way. For doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the time is come, that the Lord will rule and raign over and amongſt men upon the Earth, to the confuſion of the wicked (plot and work they never ſo deep and wiſely) and to the joy of the upright, though they may ſuffer for a little time, until this great ſhaking that we lie under, be quite paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over: But know this for truth; That if you go about to build up Sions Walls before theſe forenam'd, and ſuch like Rubbidge be removed, no good foundation will be found to build upon, and then the work may be in danger to fall, if the Fox climb up upon it; but be of good courage, and the Lord will help and proſper you;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehe.</hi> 4 23. <hi>Nehe.</hi> 6.1.2.</note> and beware of the Enemies plots, eſpecially ſuch as are written in the Scriptures, and make thoſe Types or Figures your rule; for it is written for our Inſtruction, (upon whom the ends of the world are come) as well as any other Scripture; and once more I ſay, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with; therefore lay it to heart, that a confuſed choiſe of men to Govern and make Laws either in Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, will ever be uſeleſs and unprofitable. Neither look for help by any, whom the Lord hath diſowned in his great breaches, except they appear right <hi>Huſhaes.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>An End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
